Now that we understand how DES works, let's look at a few attacks on DES,
现在我们理解了DES攻击如何实现的，接下来我们来看几个针对DES攻击的例子
and we're going to start with an attack called exhaustive search.
我们将以穷举攻击开始
So our goal here is basically that given a few input-output pairs, (mi, ci),
我们的目标是对给出的输入输出对(mi,ci)
our goal is to find the key that maps these m's to the c's.
找到能够将m映射到c的密钥
In other words, our goal is to find the key that maps m1, m2, m3 into c1, c2, c3,
换句话说我们的目标是找到能将m1, m2, m3映射到c1, c2, c3的密钥
and as I said, our goal is to find the key that does this mapping.
正如我说过的，我们要找到完成这个映射的密钥
The first question is, how do we know that this key is unique?
首先要解决的问题是，我们怎么能知道这个密钥是唯一的？
And so, let's do a little bit of analysis to show that in fact
所以，让我们做一些分析来证明
just one pair is enough to completely constrain a DES key,
事实上，一对输入输出就足以完全限制住一个DES密钥了
and that's why this question makes sense.
所以这个问题可以解答
OK, so let's see. So we're going to prove this simple lemma.
让我们看如何证明这个简单的引理
Now let's assume that DES is what's called an ideal cipher.
现在假设DES是理想密码
So what is an ideal cipher? Basically we're going to pretend like DES is made up of
什么是理想密码？我们假定DES由
random invertible functions. In other words, for every key, DES implements a random invertible function.
随机可逆函数组成。换句话说，对每一个密钥，DES都应用了一个随机可逆函数
Since there are 2^56 keys in DES, we're going to pretend like DES really is a collection
由于DES中有2^56个密钥 我们假设DES是
of 2^56 functions that are invertible from ^64 to ^64. OK? So of course,
由2^56个函数组成的集合 这些函数在64位字符串上可逆 当然
DES is not a collection of 2^56 random functions, but we can idealize about the cipher and pretend
DES不是2^56个随机函数的集合 但是我们可以将密码理想化 假设
that it is such a collection. Then what can we say?
它是这样一个集合 这样我们能得到什么？
Then in fact it turns out that just given one message and ciphertext, you just give me
这样事实上证明仅给出一个消息和密文 只给出一对
one pair, message and ciphertext, there's already only one key that maps this message to that ciphertext.
消息和密文 这就已经使得仅有一个密钥能将这个信息映射成那个密文
So already just given one pair m and c, I can ask you, find me the key that maps m to c,
所以对已给出的一对m,c 我问你 如何找出将m映射成c的密钥
and the solution is very likely to be unique. In fact it's going to be unique with probability roughly 99.5%.
而且结果很可能是唯一的 事实上 这有大概99.5%的可能性
I should say that this statement is true for all m and c, and the probability is just over the choice
我要说这对所有的m和c都成立  而且这个可能性只在于
of the random permutations that make up the cipher.
如何选择组成密码的随机排列
So let's write a proof. This is fairly straightforward. So what we're basically asking is,
所以让我们写下一个证明 这是非常浅显易懂的 所以我们要问的是
what's the probability that there exists some key that's not equal to k such that,
存在不为k的密钥使得…
well, c we know is equal to DES(k, m) by defintion of c and m, but we're asking how likely is it
嗯 由c和m的定义已知c=DES(k,m) 我们要问
that there's this other key, k-prime, that also satisfies this equality?
存在其他密钥k' 同样满足这个等式的可能性是多少
You realize that if this is true, if such a key k-prime exists, then just given m and c,
你意识到如果这为真 如果这样的k’存在 那么仅给出m和c
you can't decide whether the right key is k or k-prime, because both of them work. OK?
你不能决定正确的密钥是k还是k' 因为它们都管用 对吧
But I want to argue that this happens with low probability.
但是我想说明的是 这发生的概率很低
Well, so what does it mean that there exists a key k-prime that satisfies this relation?
存在密钥k’满足这个关系的意味着什么
Well, we're asking, what's the probability that the first key, the all-zero key, satisfies it?
我们要问 第一个密钥 全0的密钥满足关系的可能性是多少
Or, the second key satisfies it. Or, the third key satisfies it. And so on and so forth.
或者第二个密钥满足它的概率 或者第三个 以此类推
So by the union bound, we can bound this probability by the sum over all keys k-prime,
所以根据集合上界 我们可以用所有密钥k'的和界定这个概率
over all 56-bit keys, of the probability that DES(k,m) is equal to DES(k-prime, m).
用所有56位的密钥 界定DES(k,m)=DES(k',m)的概率
OK? So we're asking, basically, what is this probability, for a fixed key k-prime,
对吧 所以我们问 对一个固定的密钥k’
that it happens to collide with the key k at the message m? Well, let's think about this for a second.
它与密钥k关于信息m碰撞的概率是多少 嗯 让我们考虑一下
Let's fix this value, let's suppose it's some fixed value. And then we're asking,
让我们确定它的值 假设它是确定的值 然后问
how likely is it that a random permutation, pi k-prime, at the point m,
随机序列πk'在m处恰好产生
happens to produce exactly the same output as the key k at the point m?
相同输出的概率是多少
Well, it's not difficult to answer and see that in fact this is, for a single key k-prime,
这不难解答 可以看出事实上对每一个单独的k’
the probability is at most one over 2^64. Right? There are 2^64 possible outputs for the permutation,
其概率最多是1/(2^64) 对吧 对这个序列有2^64个可能的输出
what's the probability that it lands exactly on this output, well, it's one over 2^64.
它恰好出现这一个输出的概率就是1/(2^64)
And we're summing over all 2^56 keys, so we just multiply the two,
然后我们把所有2^56个密钥的都加起来 仅需将这两个相乘
we get one over 2^8, which is basically one over 256. OK? So the probability
我们得到1/(2^8)  也就是1/256 对吧 所以
that the key is not unique is one over 256, therefore the probability that it is unique
密钥不唯一的概率是1/256 因此它唯一的概率
is one minus that, which is 99.5%. OK? So already, if you give me one plaintext-ciphertext pair,
是1-1/256 也就是99.5%  对吧 所以如果你给我一个明文-密文对
the key is completely determined. There's only one key that will map that plaintext
密钥就已经被决定了 只有一个密钥会将那个明文
to that ciphertext, and the question is just, can you find that key?
映射成那个密文 问题是 你能找到那个密钥吗
Now it turns out in fact if you give me two pairs, so you give me m1 and m2,
结果发现事实上如果你给我那样的两对 给出m1, m2
and their corresponding outputs, c1 and c2, the probability basically
和它们相关的输出c1和c2 基本的概率是
just do exactly the same analysis, the probability basically becomes one.
做同样的分析 这个概率就是1
That there's only one such key. OK, essentially, this is very, very, very close to 1,
就是仅有一个这样的密钥 好吧 本质上是非常非常接近1
and basically it says given two pairs, it's very very likely that only one key
基本可以说给出两对明文密文 非常可能仅有一个密钥
will map this pair of messages to this pair of ciphertexts, and as a result again,
能够将这对信息映射成这对密文 因此
we can ask, well, find me that unique key. And by the way, the same is true for AES,
我们可以问 找出那个唯一的密钥 顺便一提 这对AES也是一样的
if you look at AES-128, again, just given two input-output pairs,
如果是AES128的情况 只给出两对输入输出
there's going to be only one key with very high probability. So essentially now
有很大的概率仅有一个密钥 所以本质上
we can ask this exhaustive search problem, I give you two or three pairs, and I ask you,
我们可以提出这个穷举搜索问题 我给你两对或三对输入输出 然后问你
well, find me the key. So how are you going to do it? Well, you're going to do it by exhaustive search,
找出这个密钥 那你要怎么做 你将通过穷搜索来做到
essentially by trying all possible keys, one by one, until you find the right one.
本质上是通过一个一个尝试所有可能的密钥 直到你找到正确的那一个
So this is what's known as the DES challenge. So let me explain how the DES challenge worked.
所以这被称作DES难题 让我解释一下它是如何做到的
The challenge was issued by a company called RSA, and what they did is basically,
这个难题是被RSA公司放出的 他们做的事情基本上就是
they published a number of ciphertexts, but three of the ciphertexts had known plaintexts.
发布一些密文 但是其中三个密文有已知明文
So in particular, what they did is they took the message here: The unknown message is, colon,
他们特别要做的是 将这里的信息 “未知信息是 ：XXXX...”
and you can see they broke it up into blocks. If you look at these, these are basically
拆分成组 如果你观察这些组 他们基本上都是
eight-byte blocks. Eight bytes, as you know, is 64 bits, right, so each of these is 64 bits.
8字节的分组 如你所知 8个字节是64位 所以每个分组是64位
And then they encrypted them using a secret key. They encrypted them all using the same
然后他们用一个秘密密钥加密这些分组 他们用同样的密钥加密它们
secret key to get three ciphertexts. So this gives us three plaintext-ciphertext pairs,
来得到三个密文 所以这就给我们提供了三个明文密文对
and then they gave us a whole bunch of other ciphertexts, you know, c4, c5, c6,
而且也给了我们很多其他密文如c4，c5，c6
and the challenge was, decrypt these guys using the key that you found
现在面临的挑战是 用你通过对已给出的前三个明文密文对进行穷举搜索找到的密钥
from an exhaustive search over the first three pairs that you were given.
解密这些东西
OK. So that was called the DES challenge, and let me tell you a little bit
所以这叫做DES难题 让我告诉你需要多长时间解决它
about how long it took to solve it. So interestingly, in 1997, using an Internet search,
有趣的是 在1997年 通过互联网搜索
using distributed.net, basically, they were able to search through enough of the keyspace
使用分布式网络 通过搜索足够的秘钥空间
to find the correct key in about three months. You realize the keyspace has size 2^56,
能在三个月内找到那个正确的密钥 密钥的大小是2^56
but on average you only have to search through half the keyspace to find the key,
但是平均来说 你只需搜索一半的密钥空间就能找到这个密钥
and so it took them three months. Then, kind of a miraculous thing happened.
所以这花费了他们3个月 然后不可思议的事情发生了
The EFF actually contracted Paul Kocher to build special-purpose hardware to break DES.
EFF与Paul Kocher签订合约 为制造专用硬件来攻破DES
This was a machine called Deep Crack. It cost about 250,000 dollars, and it broke
这就是叫做Deep Crack的机器 它大概花费25万美元
the next DES challenge in only three days. Interestingly, by the way, RSA said that
它仅用三天就攻破了下一个DES难题 顺便一提 有趣的是 RSA说
they would pay ten thousand dollars for each solution of a challenge, so you can see
他们将会为每个难题的解答支付1万美元 所以你会发现
that this is not quite economical. They spent 250K, they got ten thousand dollars
这并不是很经济合算 他们花费25万美元而解决问题仅得到1万美元
for solving the challenge. The next thing that happened is in 1999,
下一件事情发生在1999年
RSA issued another challenge, and they said, well, I'm gonna solve it in half the time
RSA发布了另一个难题 而且他们说 用之前解决方案一半时间就能解决
of the previous solution, and so using both Deep Crack and the Internet search together,
所以在同时使用Deep Crack和互联网搜索的情况下
they were able to break DES in 22 hours.
他们仅用22小时就破解了DES
So the bottom line here is, essentially, DES is completely dead.
所以底线是 事实上DES完全不起作用
Essentially, if you forget, or you lose your DES 56-bit key, don't worry”
如果你忘记或者遗失了DES-56位的密钥 不要担心
within 22 hours, you can actually recover it and in fact, anyone can recover it, and so
在22小时内 你就能恢复它而且事实上任何人都能做到
DES essentially is dead and no longer secure. And just kind of a final nail in the coffin,
所以DES并不起作用也不再安全 有点像棺材上最后一个钉子
as hardware technology improved, there was another project called COPACABANA that used FPGAs,
随着硬件技术发展 出现另外一个使用FPGA的项目 叫做COPACABANA
just off-the-shelf FPGAs, only 120 FPGAs. It only cost 10,000 dollars. And they were able to break,
使用现货供应的FPGA 只用了120个 仅花1万美元 他们就能破解
to do an exhaustive key search in about seven days. So very, very cheap hardware, just off the shelf,
在7天内完成穷举密钥搜索 所以非常非常廉价的硬件 刚刚上市
you can break DES already very quickly. So the lesson from all this is essentially,
你已经可以非常快速地破解DES 所以这一系列中的这一课很关键
56-bit ciphers are totally, totally dead. And so the question is what to do.
56位的密码完全不起作用 所以问题是该怎么做
People really liked DES, it was deployed in a lot of places, there were a lot of implementations,
人们真的喜欢DES 它被使用在许多地方 许多的应用软件
there was a lot of hardware support for it, so the question was what to do.
也有很多支持它的硬件 所以问题是该怎么办
And so the first thing that came to mind is, well maybe we can take DES
所以第一个进入我们脑海的想法是 也许我们可以将DES
and we can kind of artificially expand the key size, so we strengthen it against
在某种程度上人工增大密钥的长度 所以我们加长它来抵御
this exhaustive search attack. And the first idea that comes to mind is basically,
穷举搜索攻击 第一个想到的主意是
well, let's iterate the block cipher a couple of times. And this is what's called Triple DES.
多次迭代分组密码 这被称作三重DES
So Triple DES is a general construction. Basically it says the following.
所以三重DES是一个总体的结构 它的具体如下
Suppose you gave me a block cipher E. So here, it has a keyspace K,
如果你给我一个分组密码E 在这 有一个密钥空间K
it has a message space M, and an output space of course M as well.
和消息空间M 当然也有输出空间M
Let's define the triple construction, which now uses three keys, and it's defined as follows,
让我们定义这个三重结构 它现在使用三个密钥 定义如下
basically, here, the triple construction uses three independent keys, encrypts the same
这个三重结构使用三个独立的密钥 加密同样的分组消息
message block as before, and what it does is, it will encrpyt using the key k3,
正如之前一样 它做的工作是 使用密钥K3加密分组消息
then it will decrypt using the key k2, then it will encrypt again using the key k1.
然后用密钥K2解密 再用密钥K1加密
OK so basically encrpyting three times, using three independent keys.
所以基本上是加密三次 使用三个独立的密钥
You might be wondering, why is it doing E, D, E, why not just do E, E, E?
你可能会疑惑 为什么是加密-解密-加密的顺序 而不是三次加密
Why do we have to have a D in the middle? Well, that's just for, uh, kind of a hack.
为什么我们在中间要解密一次 这是为了防止某种意义上的相撞
You notice what happens if you set up k1 equals k2 equals k3? What happens if all three keys
注意观察如果你将k1k2k3都设成相等会发生什么 如果三个密钥
are the same? Well, basically, what will happen is, one E and one D would cancel,
都相等会是什么情况呢 会发生一次加密和解密相抵消
and you would just get normal DES out. So it's just a hack so that if you have a hardware implementation
然后你将仅得到一般DES加密的结果 所以这就是一种碰撞 如果你有一个实现三重DES的硬件设施
of Triple DES, you can set all three keys to be the same, and you'll get a hardware implementation
你可以将所有三个密钥设成一样 然后你就得到了实现单一
of single DES. Of course it'll be three times as slow as a regular impelmentation of single DES,
DES的硬件 当然它的速度会是常规单一DES实现的三分之一罢了
but nevertheless, it's still an option. OK, so for Triple DES now we get a key size
然而 这也是一种选择 对于三重DES我们得到的密钥长度是
that's 3 times 56, which is 168 bits; this is, 168 bits is way too long to do an exhaustive search on.
3*56也就是168位  168位长到了无法实施穷举搜索的程度
That will take time 2^168, which is more than all the machines on earth working for ten years
穷搜索将花费是时间是2^168 地球上所有机器运行10年也不能
would be able to do. Unfortunately, of course, the cipher is three times slower than DES.
完成的工作 不幸的是 当然这个密码也会比DES慢两倍
So this is a real problem with Triple DES. Now I want to mention that in fact you might think
所以这才是三重DES真正的问题 现在我想说得是 你也许认为
Triple DES has security 2^168, but in fact, there is a simple attack that runs in time 2^118,
三重DES在2^168的时间内是安全的 但事实上 有一个简单攻击运行时间为2^118
and I want to show you how that attack works. OK? So” but in fact 2^118 is still a large number.
我们来看那个攻击是如何做到的 实际上2^118依然是一个很大的数
In fact, anything that's, kind of, bigger than 2^90 is considered sufficiently secure.
事实上 任何大于2^90的时间都可以认为足够安全
2^118 is definitely sufficiently secure against exhaustive search,
2^118当然对穷举搜索来说足够安全
and generally is considered a high enough level of security.
而且一般被认为是足够高的安全等级
So clearly Triple DES is three times as slow as DES. So the question is,
所以明显三重DES的速度是DES的三分之一 问题是
why did they repeat the cipher three times? Why not repeat the cipher just two times,
为什么将密码重复三次 为什么不仅将密码重复两次
or in particular, the question is, what's wrong with double DES?
更具体地说 二重DES存在什么问题呢
So here we have double DES. Basically you see it uses only two keys, and it uses only
我们来看这个二重DES 可以看到只用两个密钥 只需要
two applications of the block cipher, and as a result it's only going to be twice as slow as DES,
两次运用分组密码 结果速度只会比DES慢一倍
not three times as slow as DES. Well, the key length for double DES is 2 times 56, which is
而不是两倍 二重DES的密钥长度是2*56
112 bits, and in fact doing exhaustive search on a space of 112 bits is too much.
也就是112比特 事实上112位秘钥空间对穷举搜索也太长了
2^112 is too big of a number to do exhaustive search over such a large space.
穷举搜索无法在2^112如此大的空间中进行
So the question is, what's wrong with this construction. Well, it turns out
因而问题变成 这个结构有什么问题
this construction is completely insecure, and I want to show you an attack.
事实上 这个结构完全不安全 我给你们看一个攻击实例
So, suppose I'm given a bunch of inputs, say m1 to m10, and I'm given the corresponding outputs
假设我有一些输入 m1到m10 和对应的输出c1到c10
c1 to c10. What's my goal? Well, my goal is basically to find keys, you know, a pair of keys k1, k2,
我的目标是什么 我的目标是找出密钥 也就是一对密钥k1,k2
such that if I encrypt the message M using these keys, in other words if I do this encryption,
如果我用这两个密钥加密消息M 换句话说如果我对消息
this double DES encryption, then I get the ciphertext vector that was given to me.
进行二重DES加密 我将会得到已给出的密文向量
OK, so our goal is to solve this equation here. Now you stare at this equation a little bit,
所以我们的目标是解决这里的等式 你们看一会这个等式
and you realize, hey wait a minute, I can rewrite it in kind of an interesting way;
过一会而 我可以用一种有意思的方式重写它
I can apply the decryption algorithm, and then what I'll get is that I'm really looking for
我可以使用解密算法 然后我将得到我期望的
keys k1, k2 that satisfy this equation here, where basically all I did is I applied
密钥k1,k2 它们满足这里的等式 我所做的就是
the decryption algorithm using k1 to both sides. OK, now whenever you see an equation like this,
使用k1对两边进行解密 好 无论什么时候你看到像这样的等式
what just happened here is that we separated our variables into two sides,
需要做的事情是 我们将变量分割成两部分
the variables now appear on independent sides of the equation, and that usually means
现在变量单独出现在等式两边 这意味着
that there is a faster attack than exhaustive search, and in fact this attack is called
有一个比穷举搜索更快的攻击 事实上这个攻击被叫做
a meet-in-the-middle attack, where really the meet-in-the-middle is going to somehow
中间人攻击 而这中攻击将以某种方式
attack this particular point in the construction. OK, so we're going to try and find a key
就这一点来攻击这个结构 好 我们尝试找出一个密钥
that maps m to a particular value here, and maps c to the same value.
能将m映射成这里的一个特定值 而且将c映射成相同的值
OK, so let me show you how the attack works. So the first thing we're going to do is
我们来看这个攻击是如何做到的 首先
we're going to build a table. Here, let me clear up some space here.
我们要建一个表 在这 让我清理出一些空间
The first step is to build a table that for all possible values of k2,
第一步是建一个表 写出k2所有可能的值
encrypts m under that value. OK, so here we have this table, so you notice
用其加密m得到的值记在表上 所以在我们这有了这张表
these are all 2^56 Single DES keys, OK, so the table has 2^56 entries,
这里是所有2^56个一重DES的密钥 所以这个表有2^56项
and what we do is basically, for each entry, we compute the encryption of m
我们要做的是计算每一项 在用相应密钥加密m得到的结果
under the appropriate key. So this is the encryption of m under the all-zero key,
所以这是用全0密钥加密m的结果
the encryption of m under the one key, and at the bottom, we have the encryption of m
在一个密钥下加密m的结果 在底部是
under the all-one key. OK, so there are 2^56 entries, and we sort this table based on the second column.
用全1的密钥加密m的结果 所以这有2^56个项 然后我们根据第二列对这个表进行排序
OK, so far, so good. So by the way this takes times to build this table takes time 2^56,
目前一切良好 顺便一说建立这张表需要2^56的时间
and I guess we also want to sort, sorting takes n log n time, so it's 2^56 times log 2^56. OK.
我们也需要排序 排序需要nlogn的时间所以就是 2^56*log2^56
So now that we have this table, we've essentially built all possible values
现在我们得到了这张表 我们本质上得到了
in the forward direction for this point.
第一重加密的所有可能的值
Now what we're going to do is this meet-in-the-middle attack,
现在我们要做的就是中间人攻击
where now we try to go in the reverse direction with all possible keys k.
现在我们尝试用所有可能的密钥k向前推
Essentially we compute the decryption of c under all possible keys k1.
本质上我们就是计算 所有可能的密钥k1对c解密的结果
OK, so now for each potential decryption, remember the table holds all possible values
好了 所以现在记下每一个潜在的解密结果 记住这张表里的在中间点上所有可能的值
in the midpoint, so then for each possible decrpytion, we check, hey, is the decryption in the table,
然后对每一个可能的解密结果 我们检查它是否在表格中
in the second column in the table? If it is in the table, then aha, we found the match,
是否在表格的第二列中 如果是的话 哈 我们找到了这个配对
and then what do we know? We know that essentially, well, we found the match, so we know that
现在我们知道了什么 我们知道 本质上我们找到了这个配对
say for example a decryption using a particular key k1 happened to match this entry in the table,
举例来说 用特定的密钥k1解密的情况下 正好与表格中的这项相匹配
say, k2 or more generally ki, then we know that the encryption of m under ki
对k2或者更一般的情况下的ki 我们知道用ki加密m的结果
is equal to the decryption of c under k. OK, so we kind of build this meet-in-the-middle,
等于用k加密c的结果 好 所以我们差不多已经建立了中间相遇模型
where the two sides, you know, the encryption of m under ki and the decryption of c under k,
这两边 分别是用ki加密m的结果和用k加密c的结果
collided, but if they collided, then we know that in fact this pair, ki and k, is equal to
如果它们碰撞了 我们就知道 事实上这一对ki和k
the pair that we're looking for. And so we've just solved our challenge.
就是我们要找的那一对秘钥 所以我们解决了这一难题
So now let's look at what's the running time of this? Well, we had to build a table,
现在让我们来看一下这个的运行时间是多少 我们需要做一个表格
and sort it, and then for all possible decryptions, we had to do a search through the table.
然后排序 然后对所有可能的解密结果 在表格中搜索
So there were 2^56 possible decryptions, each search in a sorted table takes log(2^56) time,
所以有2^56个可能的解密结果 每次在已排序的表格中搜素需要log(2^56)的时间
if you just work it out this turns out to be 2^63, which is way, way, way, way, way smaller
如果你把它算出来就是2^63 这比2^112小得多
than 2^112. OK, so this is a serious attack, it's probably doable today, that runs in a total time
所以这是一个糟糕的攻击 在今天是可行的 完全可以接受 2^63的时间
of 2^63, which is about the same time as the exhaustive search attack on DES.
用时差不多和DES穷举搜索攻击一样
So really, double DES really didn't solve the exhaustive search problem,
所以二重DES不能解决穷举搜素问题
because, well, there's an attack on it that runs in about the same time
因为对此有一个攻击 其运行时间差不多
as exhaustive search on single DES. Now someone might complain
跟一次DES的穷举搜索攻击相等 有些人可能会抱怨
that in fact this algorithm, well, we have to store this big table,
因为事实上这个算法 必须要存储这张大表
so it takes up a lot of space, but you know, so be it. Nevertheless, the running time
需要占用很大的空间 那又怎样 无论如何 运行时间
is still quite small or significantly smaller than 2^112.
还是很小 或者说比2^112小很多
Now you notice, by the way, this same attack applies to Triple DES.
顺便说一句 现在你应该注意到了 一样的攻击可以应用在三重DES上
What you would do is you would implement the meet-in-the-middle attack against this point,
你所要做的就是对这一点实现中间人攻击
you would build a table of size 2^56 of all possible encryptions of m,
你要建立一张2^56大的表 包含m所有可能的加密结果
and then you would try to decrypt with all 2^112 keys until you find a collision,
然后你尝试用2^112个密钥进行解密 直到你找到碰撞的那一个
and when you find a collision, you have basically found k1, k2, k3.
当遇到碰撞时 你就已经发现了k1,k2,k3
OK, so even Triple DES has an attack that basically explores only 2^112 possible keys.
所以即使是三重DES也存在穷搜索2^112个可能的密钥就能实现的攻击
But 2^112 is a large enough number, so Triple DES in fact, as far as we know,
但是2^112是一个足够大的数 所以三重DES在目前来说
is sufficiently secure. I should mention that Triple DES is actually a NIST standard,
是足够安全的 我应该提醒的是 三重DES实际上是NIST的标准
and so Triple DES is actually used quite a bit, and in fact DES should never ever ever be used,
所以三重DES应用广泛 而且事实上 DES从来就不应该被使用
if for some reason you're forced to use some version of DES, use Triple DES, not DES.
如果因为某些原因你必须使用DES的某些版本 使用三重DES而不是DES
OK, I want to mention one more method for strengthening DES against exhaustive search attacks.
我还想再多说一个扩展DES以抵抗穷举搜索攻击的方法
This method actually is not standardized by NIST, because it doesn't defend against
这个方法实际上没有被NIST标准化 因为它不能抵抗
more subtle attacks on DES, but nevertheless if all you're worried about is exhaustive search,
更精妙的对DES的攻击 然而你所要担心的就是穷举搜索
and you don't want to pay the performance penalties of Triple DES, then this is an interesting idea.
而且你不想付出使用三重DES的代价 那么这个方法就是一个有趣的主意
So let me show you how it works. So let E be a block cipher that operates on n-bit blocks.
让我向你展示它是如何做到的 假设E是在n位分组上操作的分组密码
We're going to define the EX construction, and for DES we're going to get DESX, to be the following.
我们将接下来要定义EX结构 对DES来说 我们将得到DESX 如下
So we use three keys, k1, k2, k3, and then basically before encrpytion, we XOR with k3,
所以我们使用三个密钥k1k2k3 在加密之前与K3异或
then we encrypt using k2, and then after encryption we XOR with k1. That's it.
然后用K2加密 加密之后再与k1异或 就是这样
That's the whole construction. So basically, you'll notice it doesn't slow the block cipher much,
这就是整个结构 所以你会看到 它不会拖慢分组密码多少
because all we did is we applied the cipher plus two additional XORs, which are super fast.
因为我们做的仅是使用这个密码再加上两个额外的异或 异或的速度非常快
The key length for this is in fact, well, we got two keys that are as long as the block size,
这里密钥的长度实际上 嗯 我们有两个跟分组一样大小的密钥
and we got one key that's as long as the key size, so the total is 184 bits.
还有一个跟密钥大小一样的 所以一共是184位
Now, it turns out actually the best attack that's known is actually an attack that takes time 2^120,
事实证明已知的最好攻击耗时2^120
and this is actually fairly simple. So it's a generic attack on EX, it will always take time basically
那其实很简单 所以这是一个一般EX攻击 它所需的时间是
block size plus the key size, and it's a simple homework problem
分组大小加上密钥大小 这是一个简单的家庭作业
for you to try to figure out this attack. I think this is a good exercise.
为了让你们弄懂这个攻击 我想这是一个很好的练习
OK, in fact there is some analysis to show that there is no exhaustive search attack
好了事实上有分析表明没有穷举搜索攻击
on this type of construction, so it's a fine construction against exhaustive search,
可以破解这种结构 所以这是可以抵抗穷举搜索的很好的结构
but there are more subtle attacks on DES that we'll talk about in the next segment,
但是还有一些更精妙的DES攻击 我们将在下一节讨论
that basically this construction will not prevent.
而这种结构无法防范那些攻击
One thing that I want to point out, unfortunately I found this mistake in a number of products,
我想指出的一点是 很不幸 我在很多产品中发现这个错误
is if you just decide to XOR on the outside, or if you just decide to XOR on the inside,
那就是如果你决定在外部或者内部进行异或
as opposed to XOR-ing on both sides, which is what DESX does,
相对比与DESX那样在两边异或的情况
you notice DESX XORs both on the outside and on the inside,
你会注意到DESX在内部和外部都进行异或
If you just do one of them, then basically this construction does nothing
如果你只做其中一个 那么这个结构对保证你密码的安全性
to secure your cipher. It'll still be as vulnerable to exhaustive search
将毫无用处 它将在穷举搜索面前脆弱得像
as the original block cipher E. OK, so this is another homework problem,
原本的分组密码E一样 好了 所以这就是另一个家庭作业中的另一个问题
and actually you'll see that as part of our homeworks. OK.
实际上你会在我们的作业中看到那个问题
So this basically concludes our discussion of exhaustive search attacks,
这基本上就总结了我们对穷举搜索的讨论
and next we'll talk about more sophisticated attacks on DES.
下一次我们将讨论更复杂的DES攻击